

## Google Consumer Health Research Team

# Summary

My research interests lie in the intersection of machine learning, ubiqutous computing and health. I have published 22 peer-reviewed papers on top venues in machine learning(NeurIPS, ICLR, CHIL, CVPR, WACV), mobile and ubiquitous computing (CHI, IMWUT/Ubicomp), and health & biomedical engineering (TBME, JBHI, EMBC, PLOS). My research have gained significant attention from both academia and industry and been featured as oral presentations at NeurIPS and ICLR as well as on various public media including IEEE Spectrum, ACM TechNews, GeekWire, ZDNet, UW news.

### Education \_\_\_\_\_

### University of Washington, Seattle

Seattle, WA, USA

Sep 2018 - March 2023

Ph.D. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

- Google PhD Fellow
- Research Areas: Machine Learning, Mobile & Ubiquitous Computing, Health
- Advisors: Shwetak Patel & Daniel McDuff

#### **University of Massachusetts, Amherst**

Amherst, MA, USA

**B.S. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE** 

Sep 2014 - June 2018

- Graduated with Honors + Outstanding Undergraduate Achievement Award + 21st Century Leaders Award
- Research Area: Mobile & Ubiquitous Computing, Mobile Health, Rehabilitation Technology
- Advisor: Sunghoon Ivan Lee

# Professional Experience \_\_\_\_\_

2023-Now	Google Consumer Health Research, Full-time Research Scientist
2018-2023	University of Washington + Ubiquitous Computing Lab, Graduate Research Assistant
2021-2023	Google Consumer Health Research, Research Intern
2021	Microsoft Research + Human Understanding and Empathy Team, Research Intern (June-Sep)
2020-2021	OctoML + Machine Learning System Team , Research Intern (Nov - June)
2019	Allen Institute for Artificial Intelligence (AI2), Research Intern (June-Sep)
2016-2018	UMass Amherst + Advanced Human Health Analytics Lab, Undergraduate Research Assistant

# Awards \_\_\_\_\_

- 2023 Oral, Top 1.6% and Notable 5%, ICLR 2023 [21]
- 2022 Google PhD Fellowship, Three-year full support, 1 out 0f 72 worldwide recipients, Google AI
- 2022 **Oral, Top 1%**, NeurIPS 2022 [19]
- 2020 Oral, Top 1%, NeurIPS 2020 [5]
- 2019 Cover Article Nominee, IEEE JBHI [1]
- 2018 Glerum Family Endowed Fellowship, University of Washington

**21st Century Leaders Award**, Top 10 most exceptional graduates out of 5500, UMass Amherst **Outstanding Undergraduate Achievement Award**, UMass Amherst

2017 Rising Researcher Award, Highest honor for undergraduate research, UMass Amherst Outstanding Undergraduate Course Assistant Award, UMass Amherst NSF Student Travel Award, National Science Foundation Honors College Research Assistant Fellowship, UMass Amherst

2014-2018 University Merit Director's Scholarship, UMass Amherst

Publications		

# **UNDER REVIEW/REVISION**

- [6] Akshay Paruchuri, **Xin Liu**, Yulu Pan, Shwetak Patel, Daniel McDuff, Soumyadip Sengupta, "Motion Matters: Neural Motion Transfer for Better Camera Physiological Sensing," *ICCV 2023*
- [5] Girish Narayanswamy, Yujia Liu, Yuzhe Yang, Chengqian Ma, **Xin Liu**\*, Daniel McDuff\*, Shwetak Patel\*, "BigSmall: Efficient Multi-Task Learning for Disparate Spatial and Temporal Physiological Measurements," *ICCV 2023* (\* **senior author**)
- [4] Ziqi Gao, Jianguo Chen, Junliang Xing, Shwetak Patel, Yuanchun Shi, **Xin Liu**\*, Yuntao Wang\*, "MMTSA: Multimodal Temporal Segment Attention Network for Efficient Human Activity Recognition," *IMWUT/Ubicomp 2023 (\* senior author)*
- [3] Xin Liu, Xiaoyu Zhang, Yuntao Wang, Shwetak Patel, Daniel McDuff, "Deep Physiological Sensing Toolbox," NeurIPS 2023
- [2] Brian Hill, **Xin Liu**, Daniel McDuff, "Learning Higher-Order Dynamics in Video-Based Cardiac Measurement," *IEEE Transactions on Biomedical Engineering (TBME)*
- [1] Xin Liu, Shwetak Patel, Daniel McDuff, "Camera-Based Physiological Sensing: Challenges and Future Directions," Arxiv

#### **PUBLISHED**

- [23] Jiankai Tang, Kequan Chen, Yuntao Wang, Yuanchun Shi, Shwetak Patel, Daniel McDuff, **Xin Liu**\*, "MMPD: Multi-Domain Mobile Video Physiology Dataset," *EMBC 2023 (\* senior author)*
- [22] Theodore Curran, Xin Liu, Daniel McDuff, Shwetak Patel, Eugene Yang, "Camera-based remote photoplethysmography to measure heart rate and blood pressure in ambulatory patients with cardiovascular disease: preliminary analysis," *Journal of the American College of Cardiology*
- [21] Yuzhe Yang, **Xin Liu**, Jiang Wu, Silviu Borac, Dina Katabi, Ming-Zher Poh, Daniel McDuff, "SimPer: Simple Self-Supervised Learning of Periodic Targets," *ICLR 2023* [Oral, Top 1.6%]
- [20] Yuang Li, Yuntao Wang, **Xin Liu**, Yuanchun Shi, Shao-Fu Shih, "Enabling Real-time On-chip Audio Super-Resolution for Bone Conduction Microphones," *Sensors*
- [19] Xuhai Xu, Han Zhang, Yasaman Sefidgar, Yiyi Ren, **Xin Liu**, Woosuk Seo, Jennifer Brown, Kevin Kuehn, Mike Merrill, Paula Nurius, Shwetak Patel, Tim Althoff, Margaret E. Morris, Eve Riskin, Jennifer Mankoff, Anind K. Dey, "GLOBEM: Multi-Year Datasets for Longitudinal Human Behavior Modeling Generalization," *NeurIPS 2022 Benchmark and Dataset Track* [Oral, Top 1%]
- [18] Daniel McDuff, Miah Wander, **Xin Liu**, Brian Hill, Javier Hernandez, Jonathan Lester, Tadas Baltrusaitis "SCAMPS: Synthetics for Camera Measurement of Physiological Signals," *NeurIPS 2022 Benchmark and Dataset Track*
- [17] **Xin Liu**, Brian Hill, Ziheng Jiang, Shwetak Patel, Daniel McDuff, "EfficientPhys: Enabling Simple, Fast, and Accurate Camera-Based Vitals Measurement," *IEEE/CVF Winter Conference on Applications of Computer Vision (WACV 2023)*
- [16] Xuhai Xu, **Xin Liu**, Han Zhang, Weichen Wang, Subigya Kumar Nepal, Kevin S. Kuehn, Jeremy F Huckins, Margaret E Morris, Paula S. Nurius, Eve Ann Riskin, Shwetak Patel, Tim Althoff, Andrew Campbell, Anind K. Dey, Jennifer Mankoff, "Cross-Dataset Generalization of Longitudinal Human Behavior Modeling," *Proceedings of the ACM on Interactive, Mobile, Wearable and Ubiquitous Technologies (IMWUT/Ubicomp 2023)*
- [15] **Xin Liu**, Ziheng Jiang, Shwetak Patel, Daniel McDuff, "Federated Remote Physiological Measurement with Imperfect Data," *Proceedings of the IEEE/CVF Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition Workshop, 2022*

- [14] **Xin Liu**, Yuntao Wang, Sinan Xie, Daniel McDuff, Shwetak Patel, "MobilePhys: Personalized Mobile Camera-Based Contactless Physiological Sensing," *Proceedings of the ACM on Interactive, Mobile, Wearable and Ubiquitous Technologies (IMWUT/Ubicomp 2021)*
- [13] Daniel McDuff, Javier Hernandez, **Xin Liu**, Erroll Wood, Tadas Baltrusaitis, "Using High-Fidelity Avatars to Advance Camera-based Cardiac Pulse Measurement," *IEEE Transactions on Biomedical Engineering (TBME)* 2022
- [12] Brian Hill, **Xin Liu**, Daniel McDuff, "Beat-to-beat cardiac pulse rate measurement from video," *IEEE/CVF International Conference on Computer Vision Conference Workshop*
- [11] Daniel McDuff, **Xin Liu**, Javier Hernandez, Erroll Wood, Tadas Baltrusaitis, "Synthetic Data for Multi-Parameter Camera-Based PhysiologicalSensing," *IEEE Engineering in Medicine and Biology Conference (EMBC 2021)*
- [10] Chunjong Park, Morelle Arian, **Xin Liu**, Alex Mariakakis, Leon Sasson, Shwetak Patel, Tim Althoff, "Job Performance in Athletes and Salespeople: An Observational Study of Performance, Sleep, and Mobile App Usage," *The Web Conference (WWW 2021)*,
- [9] **Xin Liu**, Ziheng Jiang, Josh Fromm, Xuhai Xu, Shwetak Patel, Daniel McDuff, "MetaPhys: Few-Shot Adaptation for Non-Contact Physiological Measurement," *ACM Conference on Health, Inference, and Learning (ACM-CHIL 2021)*Selected Media Coverage: [UW News], [ACM TechNews Headline], [IEEE Spectrum], [GeekWire]
- [8] **Xin Liu**, Yuang Li, Josh Fromm, Ziheng Jiang, Yuntao Wang, Alex Mariakakis, Shwetak Patel, "SplitSR: An End-to-End Approach to Super-Resolution on Mobile Devices," *Proceedings of the ACM on Interactive, Mobile, Wearable and Ubiquitous Technologies (IMWUT/Ubicomp 2021)*
- [7] Xuhai Xu, Jiahao Li, Tianyi Yuan, Liang He, **Xin Liu**, Yukang Yan, Yuntao Wang, Yuanchuan Shi, Jennifer Mankoff, Anind Dey, "HulaMove: Using Commodity IMU for Waist Interaction," *ACM CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI 2021)*
- [6] Kathrin Zürcher, Carl Morrow, Julien Riou, Marie Ballif, Anastasia Sideris Koch, Simon Bertschinger, **Xin Liu**, Manuja Sharma, Keren Middelkoop, Digby Warner, Robin Wood, Matthias Egger, Lukas Fenner "Novel approach to estimate tuberculosis transmission in primary care clinics in sub-Saharan Africa: protocol of a prospective study," *BMJ Open 2020*)
- [5] **Xin Liu**, Josh Fromm, Shwetak Patel, Daniel McDuff, "Multi-Task Temporal Shift Attention Networks for On-Device Contactless Vitals Measurement," *Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems*, (NeurIPS 2020) [Oral, Top 1%, 105 out of 9454 Submissions]

  Selected Media Coverage: [Microsoft Research Webinar], [Microsoft Blog], [ZDNet]
- [4] Young Lee, **Xin Liu**, Jeremy Gummeson, Sunghoon Ivan Lee, "Towards the Ambulatory Assessment of Movement Quality in Stroke Survivors using a Wrist-worn Inertial Sensor," *IEEE International Conference on Biomedical and Health Informatics (IEEE BHI 2019)*
- [3] Sunghoon Ivan Lee, **Xin Liu**, Smita Rajan, Nathan Ramasarma, Paolo Bonato, "A Novel Upper-Limb Function Measure Derived from Finger-Worn Sensor Data Collected in a Free-Living Setting," *PLOS ONE, vol. 14, no. 3, 2019*
- [2] **Xin Liu**, Smita Rajan, Nathan Ramasarma, Paolo Bonato, Sunghoon Ivan Lee, "Finger-Worn Sensors for Accurate Functional Assessment of the Upper Limbs in Real-World Settings," *IEEE Engineering in Medicine and Biology Conference (IEEE EMBC 2018)*
- [1] **Xin Liu**, Smita Rajan, Nathan Ramasarma, Paolo Bonato, Sunghoon Ivan Lee, "Finger-Worn Sensors for Accurate Functional Assessment of the Upper Limbs in Real-World Settings," *IEEE Journal of Biomedical and Health Informatics (J-BHI)*, vol.23, no.2, 2019) [Cover Article Nominee]

Teaching Experience

reacimig	, Experience	
Winter 2021/2022	TECHIN 513 Managing Data and Signal Processing, Teaching Assistant	University of Washington
Fall 2017	CS328: Mobile Health & Sensing, Teaching Assistant (Outstanding Course Assistant Award)	UMass Amherst

Mentoring \_\_\_\_\_

2022-NowYuxuan Ou, BUPT, China (Now MS student at University of Cambridge)Seattle, W2021-2022Xiaoyu Zhang, Tsinghua University, BS, (Now PhD Student at Tsinghua CS)Seattle, W2020-2022Sinan Xie, Tsinghua University, BS, (Now PhD Student at UCSD ECE)Seattle, W2020-2021Tess Despres, University of Washington, ECE, (Now PhD Student at UC Berkeley EECS)Seattle, W2020-2021Haojia Nie, University of Waterloo, CS, (Intern at ByteDance + Meta)Seattle, W2019-2020Yuang Li, BUPT, China (Now MS student at University of Cambridge)Seattle, W	2020-Now	Mentor at GIX Access Computing Program, University of Washington & Tsinghua University	Seattle, WA
2021-2022Xiaoyu Zhang, Tsinghua University, BS, (Now PhD Student at Tsinghua CS)Seattle, W2020-2022Sinan Xie, Tsinghua University, BS, (Now PhD Student at UCSD ECE)Seattle, W2020-2021Tess Despres, University of Washington, ECE, (Now PhD Student at UC Berkeley EECS)Seattle, W2020-2021Haojia Nie, University of Waterloo, CS, (Intern at ByteDance + Meta)Seattle, W2019-2020Yuang Li, BUPT, China (Now MS student at University of Cambridge)Seattle, W	2022-Now	Yujia Liu, UW ECE M.S., (Now PhD Student at )	Seattle, WA
2020-2022Sinan Xie, Tsinghua University, BS, (Now PhD Student at UCSD ECE)Seattle, W2020-2021Tess Despres, University of Washington, ECE, (Now PhD Student at UC Berkeley EECS)Seattle, W2020-2021Haojia Nie, University of Waterloo, CS, (Intern at ByteDance + Meta)Seattle, W2019-2020Yuang Li, BUPT, China (Now MS student at University of Cambridge)Seattle, W	2022-Now	Yuxuan Ou, BUPT, China (Now MS student at University of Cambridge)	Seattle, WA
2020-2021Tess Despres, University of Washington, ECE, (Now PhD Student at UC Berkeley EECS)Seattle, W2020-2021Haojia Nie, University of Waterloo, CS, (Intern at ByteDance + Meta)Seattle, W2019-2020Yuang Li, BUPT, China (Now MS student at University of Cambridge)Seattle, W	2021-2022	Xiaoyu Zhang, Tsinghua University, BS, (Now PhD Student at Tsinghua CS)	Seattle, WA
2020-2021Haojia Nie, University of Waterloo, CS, (Intern at ByteDance + Meta)Seattle, W2019-2020Yuang Li, BUPT, China (Now MS student at University of Cambridge)Seattle, W	2020-2022	Sinan Xie, Tsinghua University, BS, (Now PhD Student at UCSD ECE)	Seattle, WA
2019-2020 Yuang Li, BUPT, China (Now MS student at University of Cambridge) Seattle, W	2020-2021	Tess Despres, University of Washington, ECE, (Now PhD Student at UC Berkeley EECS)	Seattle, WA
• • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • •	2020-2021	Haojia Nie, University of Waterloo, CS, (Intern at ByteDance + Meta)	Seattle, WA
2019-2020 Yongjoon Oh, University of Washington, CSE (Now at Microsoft) Seattle, W	2019-2020	Yuang Li, BUPT, China (Now MS student at University of Cambridge)	Seattle, WA
	2019-2020	Yongjoon Oh, University of Washington, CSE (Now at Microsoft)	Seattle, WA

# Academic Service & Outreach \_\_\_\_\_

### OUTREACH

2019-2020	<b>UW Allen School</b>	PhD Visit Day	, Co-Organizer
-----------	------------------------	---------------	----------------

- 2019-2020 **UW College of Engineering K-12 Discovery Day**, Volunteer
  - 2018 UMass Women in Engineering and Computing Career Day for High School Girls, Volunteer

### ACADEMIC SERVICE

- 2020 IEEE Journal of Biomedical and Health Informatics, Reviwer
- 2020 ACM CHI, Reviwer
- 2020-2021 ACM IWMUT/Ubicomp, Reviwer
  - 2021 IEEE CVPR, Reviwer
  - 2021 NeurIPS, Reviwer
  - 2021 ICLR, Reviwer
  - 2021 UIST, Reviwer
  - 2021 ACII, Reviwer
  - 2021 IEEE Transaction of Mobile Computing, Reviwer